<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A necessarie and briefe treatise of the contagious disease of the pestilence with the causes, signes, and cures of the same. Collected and newly composed for the benefit and comfort of the vulgar sort. By W. Boraston ...</title>
            <author>Boraston, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842240</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1164:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A necessarie and briefe treatise of the contagious disease of the pestilence with the causes, signes, and cures of the same. Collected and newly composed for the benefit and comfort of the vulgar sort. By W. Boraston ...</title>
                  <author>Boraston, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop and T. Favvcet. dwelling in Grubstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:1"/>
            <p>A NECESSARIE AND BRIEFE TREATISE OF THE Contagious diſeaſe of the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> with the Cauſes, Signes, and Cures of the ſame. COLLECTED And newly Compoſed for the benefit and comfort of the vulgar ſort. <hi>BY</hi> W. BORASTON of <hi>Salop, Practitioner in Phyſicke and Chyrurgerie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by B. ALSOP and T. FAVVCET. dwelling in <hi>Grubſtreet.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVor: THO: HIGGONS, Doctor of Divinitie, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Favourer of all good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Intentions:</hi> W. BORASTON wiſheth all Proſperitie both now and euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He most Mighty <hi>ELOHIM,</hi> Creator of all things, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our grievous Sinnes, and haynous tranſgreſsions againſt his Precepts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinances, haue threatned his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to inflict vpon them, the plague of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and divers other Sickneſſes, as Holy and Divine writ teſtifieth. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the foreſaid Afflictions and manifold Diſeaſes wherewith for our ſinnes, from
<pb facs="tcp:6881:3"/> time, to time wee haue beene often pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; Wee haue not perceived (by reaſon of the cuſtome of ſinning) how horrible the ruſt and Canker of Sinne is, vntill GOD out of his wrath powreth againe his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the offenders, and thereupon haue not onely inflicted man which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally haue tranſgreſſed, but alſo all other creatures which were created and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for mans vſe, and haue cauſed the Starres to caſt downe there venomous influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vpon his creatures, in regard we would not repent and acknowledge the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of our corrupt nature, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue farther in the middeſt of all our inflictions of the Plague of Peſtilence ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through want of Charitie or diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hate haue ſought to infect others, for which I would wiſh all ſo euill diſpoſed, to preuent the puniſhments ordained for them which are ſo preſumptuous, for as <hi>CRATO</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui malitiosè peſtifera diffundit, homicida eſt proximi ſui, &amp; paenas non modo aeternas ſibi luendas ſciat, Sed in
<pb facs="tcp:6881:3"/> hoc etiam ſeculo Magiſtratus ſeueritatem experietur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And euen as this wickedneſſe and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate blindneſſe is of all men to bee abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; So the vnmeaſurable Mercy of GOD purchaſed through Contrition, Penance and Satisfaction is to be imbraced, Seeing that he in the middeſt of all our abhominations and deſeruings of extreame puniſhments, haue euer remembred them which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite of heart, and ſorrowfull for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and loſſe of GODS fauour, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them hee haue yeelded compaſsion, and haue infuded bleſsing vnto Hearbes, Stones, and Metals, for their recouerie and cure of all their Malladies, as well alſo for nutriment as preſeruation.</p>
            <p>So that wee may plainly ſee that GOD taketh not any delight in puniſhing his creatures, but rather to make vs know how deteſtable a thing ſinne is, for by it wee often looſe his diuine Fauour and Grace, So we ought with all diligence by Humility and Obedience to obtaine the ſame againe,
<pb facs="tcp:6881:4"/> and to frame our courſe of life thereafter, that we may returne to him as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thfull and obedient Children.</p>
            <p>Now euen as they which with ſtudy and trauaile haue ſought out the wonderfull Workes of God in the Firmament, are to be commended; So deſerue they not the least praiſe, which haue indeauoured to find out the properties and vertues of ſuch things which may comfort and ſuccour the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of their diſtreſſed Neighbours, And in regard the Plague of Peſtilence is ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible vnto humaine Nature, that it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeparateth the Father from the Child, the Husband from the Wife yea the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian from his Patient, and one friend from another, for their owne ſafety, as is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I therefore receiuing my Talent at the last houre, would not negligently bury it in a Muckhill.</p>
            <p>But for the reaſons aboue-ſpecified, I thought it not amiſſe (let buſie ſpeakers ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then dooers babble what they pleaſe) to beſtow ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me paines in ſetting forth ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:4"/> directions and Remedies for them that are ſubiect to the foreſaid contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sickneſſe; eſpecially, for them which are not able to fee the Phyſitians and Chyrurgians. And in regard I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes found loue and receiued friendſhip, at your Worſhips hands; I now farther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume vpon your fauor, and right godly iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with deſire to accept of this my poore Dedication in good part. And pardon the boldneſſe of your poore Neighbour in this attempt, and he ſhall euer rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your Worſhips command, W: B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:5"/>
            <head>To the Courteous and louing <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Find by Common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (Gentle Reader,) and the effects are to much ſeene and prooued amongſt vs; That amongſt many dangerous Diſeaſes which happeneth to Mans body, there are none ſo Contagious and venemous as the <hi>Plague</hi> or <hi>Pest.</hi> And foraſmuch, as the Curing of this Diſeaſe conſiſteth in remouing the cauſe, I therefore wiſh all men, to hate and abhorre Sin, and to vſe penance for the ſame. The chiefeſt cauſe being thus removed, I doubt not, but by GOD his Aſſiſtance with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and Inſtruction hereafter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you ſhall receiue benefit. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:6881:6"/> expecting the fauourable acceptation of theſe my Labours, I ſhall bee willing to conſecrate the reſidue of my ſtudies to thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6881:6"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE PESTILENCE: Wherein is ſhewed the Cauſes, with moſt certaine Preſeruatiues againſt the Infection thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His contagious Sickneſſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Peſtilence, is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing then a preſſure, Contagion and whip, which GOD out of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vſeth to chaſtice men for their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, as it is written in the 28. of <hi>Deut.</hi> ſaying; <hi>If thou wilt not obey the voyce of the Lord thy GOD, and keepe and doe his Commandements; the Lord ſhall make the Peſtilence to cleane vnto thee.</hi> For God the Creator of all things is the chiefe and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6881:7"/> principall moouer of all things created, and vſeth them as ſecondary meanes to execute puniſhment againſt the offenders. So that the Peſtilence is either Supernaturall, and immediatly commeth from GOD to Man; or Naturall, as when God puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth man hée performeth it by his creatures. Alſo, the Peſtilence ſupernaturall is to be vnderſtood two manner of wayes, that is to ſay; either when God doth it wholly from himſelfe, or elſe permiſſiuely hée ſuffereth Sathan to puniſh Man for the reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; Hée being the moſt cruell enemy both of God and man, who grieueth and repineth at mans felicitie, and enuiouſly ſéeketh to extirpate and roote out all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. Euen as the Hiſtorie of <hi>Iob</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. So that his power is alſo two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi> Hée either doth this office of himſelfe, or elſe by Inchanters and Witches, (<hi>Exod. 7, and 8.</hi>) of whom Chriſt ſpake, <hi>Act. 8. Math. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Peſtilence naturall, is alſo taken two manner of wayes: The one genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from an aſtrall Impreſſion, the other from the microcoſmus or little wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lds I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination. The Peſtilence of Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on proceedeth from the firmament of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6881:7"/> when God puniſheth man by ſecond cauſes, hée vſeth the coniunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</hi> and other Starres, Eclipſes for correction, euen as a Father chaſtiſeth his Child with the rod. The arſenicall Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurious, Antimoniall, Napelloſous, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutoſons beames of the Starres, infects the nutriment both Spirituall and Corporall. This is the generation of Peſtilence of the influence Aſtrall.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in his Booke <hi>De occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Philoſophia,</hi> ſaith; that Of imagination ſpringeth the Peſtilence, as is there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced betwéene two Brothers.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is reported, that a man hauing the Hemerhodes and the Peſtilence together, aſpecting another being ſound, infecteth him alſo; yea, very many much more, by the intuition and earneſt beholding of women, <hi>Quae ſimul menſtruorum &amp; Peſte laborant.</hi> Moreouer by the breath, heat, ſweat, ſmell, habitation, and garments from the ſteke, the Peſtilence is propagated, and créepeth from one houſe vnto another and infecteth the Inhabitants thereof, ſo that it procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of an inuiſible eſſence, Spirituell and Aſtrall, and not of any humour or liquor onely.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6881:8"/>
               <head>Preſages and judgements taken from the Superiour bodies and Conſtellations of the Heauens.</head>
               <p>AMongſt all other bodyes Celeſtiall, there are two called euill and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which are <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; by whoſe bad influence manifold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, eſpecially of the Peſtilence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: For <hi>Saturne</hi> through Cold, cauſeth Rheumes, Elephantia, &amp;c. <hi>Mars</hi> by reaſon of Heat, bringeth forth Feauers peſtilentiall, ſpitting of Blood, Plurifies and ſuch like. Conſider well the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tring of the Sunne into <hi>Aries</hi> by true Equation of the houſes and Planet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, for that influence hath more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, then haue all other influences of the whole yéere beſide, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xcept the ſuperiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Coniunctions of the Planets, or ſome great Eclipſes.) And this entring of the Sunn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into <hi>Aries</hi> paſſeth all entrings of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ua into any other Signe. Therefore conſider how the Lord of the ſixt houſe in the figur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is diſpoſed for hée is the Lord of the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>v z.</hi> You muſt conſider, whether hée be impedite or no. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f hée be impedite there ſhall be many S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kneſſes according to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6881:8"/> his nature and his houſe, that is the ſixt houſe.</p>
               <p>As for example, be it in caſe that <hi>Saturne</hi> is Lord of the ſixt houſe, and ſome earthy ſigne is in the ſame houſe, then moſt comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſickneſſe of that yéere, ſhall be of like nature, that is cold and dry. And ouer this thou muſt conſider, whether the Lord of the ſixt houſe hath any aſpect with the Lord of the houſe of Death; to him, then moſt commonly the end of thoſe ſickneſſes that are cold and dry, ſhall be death.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe, as it is declared of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of the Sunne into <hi>Aries,</hi> So muſt it be ſaid of the coniunction of the Sunne and Moone through all the yéere, marking euery nature of the Planet being in the ſixt houſe, If there be any, and the aſpects to thoſe two houſes aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Alſo conſider, whether this entring of the Sun into <hi>Aries</hi> or any of the coniunctions of the Luminaries, be in the eight houſe or no, for then it ſhall be much worſe. Note alſo, that if the Eclipſe of the Sun or Moone be in any angles of the Natiuitie of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or in any of the angles of the reuoluſion of his natiuitie, then hée ſhall ſuffer ſicknes according to the nature of the ſame angles.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6881:9"/> And if the Eclipſe be in <hi>Medio Coeli,</hi> he ſhall ſuffer hurt in his honour &amp; ſame. And if it be in the Aſcendent, hée ſhall be gréeued in his body, and ſo forth of the other houſes. But it ſhall be the worſer in caſe the Eclipſe be in the aſcendent, eſpecially, if it be the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, for that is the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of the two. Foraſmuch as the effect of the Eclipſes of the Moone is alwayes fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſpace of one yéere at the moſt, ſometime in leſſe, and for the moſt part in thrée Moneths. But the effects of the Eclipſe of the Sun is very long or it come to paſſe. Sometimes twelue yéeres, as <hi>Ptolome</hi> in his <hi>Centiloquio</hi> witneſſeth.</p>
               <p>The Aſtrologians take the judgement of the yéere, by the entring of the Sunne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aries</hi> in the firſt minute. And if it then happen, that all the ill Planets be in the eight houſe, which is the houſe of Death, they ſay; that yéere ſhall ariſe a Peſtilence and diuers other ſikneſſes, according to the nature and conditions of thoſe Planets. And if the Moone in the ſame entring bée néere vnto the coniunction of the Sun, that is to ſay, within two or <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> degrées; That yéere ſhall be a death of Peſtilence v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall, and that ſhortly after that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6881:9"/> eſpecially, at the comming of the Moone and euill Planets to infortunes: and as the infortunes be, the effects ſhall ſo appeare, be they more or leſſe.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, you muſt conſider the great coniunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the <hi>13.</hi> degrée of <hi>Scorpio</hi> as it was in the yéere <hi>1625.</hi> in the laſt of Auguſt, which coniunction changed from an ayrie triplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie into a waterie, and it was in a waterie Signe, whereof there chanced very much raine, and thereupon followed exceſſiue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mectation and moyſtening of Mans body, which by and by turned to putrifaction and thereupon enſued many perillous and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Feauers, Peſtilence and Agues as <hi>Phaierus</hi> and many others haue related, ſpecially, becauſe the coniunction of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> was exalted in the North aboue <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which <hi>Saturne</hi> is of ill influence.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, there are aſſigned ſeauen prognoſticks, preſages or ſignes of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, more common and vſually obſerued as hereafter follow: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, when in a Summer day, the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is often changed, as in the morning like to raine, and after ſtandeth ſtill clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and at laſt, the wind turneth into the South.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6881:10"/>
               <p>The ſecond is, when often in the time of Summer, the dayes ſheweth wholly obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as if it would raine and yet not raine, and then if it doe ſo continue long, it is to be feared, a great Peſtilence will after enſue.</p>
               <p>The third Signe is, when there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Flyes vpon the Earth, for this ſignifieth that the ayre may be venemous and infected.</p>
               <p>The fourth ſigne is, when the Stars doe ſéeme often to fall, for it is a token that the ayre is corrupted by many venemous va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours which aſcendeth.</p>
               <p>The fift ſigne is when Come to do ſéeme to flye in the ayre an it appeareth in Meteors, and that thoſe happeneth, when the Comet appeareth, it ſignifieth bloudſhed, warres, &amp;c. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde verſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Mors furit, vrbs rapitur, Seuit mare, Sol operitur.</l>
                  <l>Regnum mutatur plebs peſte faeme cruciatur.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The ſixt ſigne is, when many thunders and lightnings happeneth, and eſpecially from the South part.</p>
               <p>The ſeuenth is, when many Winds pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth from the South part, for they bée foule and vncleane, when theſe ſignes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, a great Peſtilence is much to bée
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6881:10"/> feared, except our Lord omnipotent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Meanes to preuent Infection, the Cauſes and Prognoſticks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clared.</head>
               <p>NOw ſhall it bée directed by what meanes euery man ought to preſerue himſelfe from this infection, And according to the ſpéech of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaying, that a man ought <hi>Diuertere a malo, ad bonum,</hi> to turne from euill and doe good, And moſt humbly <hi>Pecataſua confiteri,</hi> to confeſſe his ſinnes, for in the time of Peſtilence, Penitencie and Confeſſion are to be preferred before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Medicaments, and withall to change the place for a more pure ayre. But if it cannot bée done conueniently, in as much as poſſible may be, let all cauſes of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uitated and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uoyded, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Venerie. Alſo the Wind procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Meridian or South point, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agious &amp; infectiue naturally: Therefore in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> time of the Peſtilence, the Windowes on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame ſide the houſe ought to bée ſhut vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill one of the clocke afternoone, and let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>indowes be open towards the North part.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6881:11"/> For the ſame cauſe, let there bée no euill ſents or ſmels as from ſtables, ſtréets, fields where dead carkaſſes corrupted and putrified may annoy you, and chiefly putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Waters, as from ſincks and houſes of Office, for <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſaith; <hi>Omne putrifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ré eſt venenum.</hi> And moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we find they dye in greateſt number, where the ayre is corrupted with theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yances; For, <hi>Sicut per odorem, aromati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam cor &amp; ſpus recreantur, ita ex nocino feto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re debilitantur.</hi> Therefore the houſe is to be kept, that no infectiue ayre enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, eſpecially that which is humide and moiſt, which naturally cauſeth putrifaction in the houſe and place where one ſléepeth: For preuention thereof the ſame houſe or places ought to be ayred with fires of wood yéelding cléere flame, and withall to fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the roomes with theſe hearbes and ſéeds ſubſcribed, Bayberies, Iuniper, Vbery, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gany, Wormswood, Hyſop, Rue, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort, and of Lign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ees, let theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be inſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n at the mouth and noſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thrils, ſo that it may pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trate into the interior and inward par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p>Let all ſuperfluity and ouermuch reple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions be refrained, for <hi>Auincen in</hi> 4. <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6881:11"/> ſaith; that <hi>Illi qui repletionem ſemper cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant periodum &amp; ſinem vitae ſuae abreuiant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe, the common Bath is to bée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, for <hi>Modicum fermentum totam maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m corrumpit.</hi> Finally, communities and concurfes of people are alſo to be left off, as much as poſſible may be, leaſt the breach of the infected be receiued. But in caſe they cannot be ſhunned, let theſe remedies bée vſed which follow.</p>
               <p>When one ariſeth in the morning, by and by let him eate a little Rue waſht in cleane water, and ſprinkled with ſalt, with one or two Walnuts well clenſed, If that cannot be had, let him eate ſome bread or a toaſt intincted with Vini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, eſpecially in a turbid or cloudy day. Alſo in the time of Peſtilence, it is better to ſtay within doores, then to goe abroad into any Towne or Citie, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the houſe eſpecially in the Summer be ſprinkled with Viniger, Roſes and Vine-leaues, alſo it ſhall be good oftentimes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, to waſh the hands with water and vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to clenſe the face, and to ſmell vnto the hands waſhed as aforeſaid. It ſhall be alſo a wholſome courſe as well in Summer as winter to ſmell vnto ſower things. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6881:12"/> for thoſe that are viſitors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſicke, to take a ſpunge or piece of bread ſtéeped in viniger, and to hold it to the Noſe or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, for all acetoſus and ſower things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo cloſe the powers, and paſſages of the humours, that no venemous ayre can enter therin as by experience I haue often found. Alſo if you take Rue, Wormewood, Sage, Marigolds of each thrée handfuls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ruſe them wholly in a gallon of Ale newly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vp, and paſte it cloſe that no ayre breath out, and after that it is fined for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. houres take ſixe or ſeuen ſpoonefuls thereof mixed with the beſt Venice-triacle in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Beane, and moderately walke thereon, and doe thus euery morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yonges forth of your houſe, as long as the Sickneſſe continueth, and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s occaſion requireth to preuent the impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion of the contagious ayre.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Another Preſeruatiue.</head>
                  <p>TAke Aloes cleane waſhed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter halfe an ounce, of good Myrrhe, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arh two dragmes, of Bale Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>epared one ſcruple, of ſéed Pearle and ſcruple, of the ſirup of Lemons as much as will make it in forme of pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e, made in pills, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e thereof euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ing the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6881:12"/> weight of a great, faſting, and within one houre after, to take a little thin broth, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery or white Wine, and faſt thereon thrée houres after, and then to vſe your accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med dyet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>BVt if the body hée very coſtine and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered therewith, then may yee vſe theſe pils in quantity as aforeſaid; Euery morning for foure or fiue dayes together if néed require, and prepared as thus: Take of Rheubarb, Myrrhe, of each one dragme, Aloes two dragmes, Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>orie roo e, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron of each one ſcruple, ſirup of Roſes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tine as much as will ſuffice to make it in forme of pilles, and to take them in manner as afore directed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Another Preſeruative.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Methridate, conſerne of Roſes of each halfe an ounce, Bole Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke prepared two dragmes, mixe them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and take thereof as much as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> at once, and faſt thereon two or thrée houres after.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe you may take of Triacle of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>chus,</hi> and of Michridate of either tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dragmes, of conſerue of Roſe 3. dragme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6881:13"/> Bole Aemoniack prepared two ſcruple, of the ſéeds or roſes of Angelica two ſcruples, of the ſeeds of Citrons halfe a dragme, of the ſirup of Lemons halfe an ounce, mixe all together and take thereof the quantity of a haſſell n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, in the morning or at any time of the day elſe (if you goe into any throug of people) and faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a while after it.</p>
                  <p>There are alſo many other preſeruatiues more coſtly, yet farre more powerfull in their effects, which may be had at the hands of the Chymiſts, as <hi>Potus Peſtilentialis Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſi,</hi> whereof one dragme being taken in the morning faſting, and to ſweat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is a preſeruatiue from the Peſtilence for ſixe dayes.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond preſeruatiue is, Sulphur ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed with Myrrhe and Aloes. Halfe a dragme with Suger thereof being taken in the morning, preſerueth a man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay from all aſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l impreſſion.</p>
                  <p>The third preſeruatiue is, <hi>Zenechthon, Paracelli,</hi> which being hanged about the necke, hindereth the attractiue power of the <hi>Microciſmus</hi> or little world, which is man.</p>
                  <p>The fourth, againſt the intuition or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous aſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of women, and men as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6881:13"/> Is Chelidonia gathered in the full of the Moone, and caried aboue one.</p>
                  <p>The fift for them which are viſitors of the ſicke, let them hold in their mouth fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence, and withall let the infected a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſame inſtant hold alſo in their mouth of the rootes of <hi>Imperitoria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſixt, is the eſſence of Harts and Storkes bloud.</p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth, which is moſt potent and powerfull, is <hi>Alexipharmacum Spagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> whereof being taken in a morning, the quantity of a Beane or leſſe, with ſugar, or in any other conuenient liquor, hath a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous effect.</p>
                  <p>Alſo for correcting of the ayre, <hi>R. Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuris lib. ſs. Thuris zij. Mirrhae z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>j. ſs. aſſae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidae z. ſs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tur &amp; miſceantur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this powder adde a double quantiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ortex or ſhells of Bayberies, of white Amber halfe a part. Take of this powder two dragmes, and caſt it vpon coales, and make a perfume thereof dayly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wiſe or thrice.</p>
                  <p>For want of this powder you may take the wood of Iuniper, and vſe it in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but it is nothing ſo good as the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6881:14"/>
               <head>Rules to bee obſerued in Common communities.</head>
               <p>SVch things as doe rarifie and ſubtile the ſpirit interior, are Saffron, Caſſia, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtula, Plannton, with mirth in meaſure, thoſe doe ſpecially ſerue in common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, and Companies, where quickly one is infected of another. The eyes are obſcured and darkned by an infectiue ayre, if a man carry not the foreſaid things or ſuch like in his hand. Therefore it ſhall be a ſafe courſe to waſh the eyes, mouth and hands oftentimes in the day, with Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water mixt with Viniger as aforeſaid, but if both cannot bée had, let Viniger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone he vſed. This being obſerued, thou mayeſt with more ſecuritie enter into any company.</p>
               <p>To kéepe the body ſoluble is thought to be an effectuall remedie, if it bée not laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue naturally, let it bée prouoked artificial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſuppoſitors, for which purpoſe alſo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the <hi>Pillulae Peſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lentiales</hi> which may bée had at the Apothecaries. Let there bée alſo fire made in the Houſe, becauſe it much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth Celeſtiall impreſſion, and clarifieth the ayre,</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6881:14"/>
               <p>To take Triacle is alſo profitable and good, as well for the ſicke as while I meane the right Venice-triacle, or Treacle of <hi>Andromochus</hi> (or Iene-triacle) if it bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred twice in a day with pure and cléere wine, Béere or Roſe-water, in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a ſmall Beane or Peaſe at each time, mixt with two ſpoonefuls of any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Liquors: Let Dinner bée defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vntill midday, whereby the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle, may haue its operation in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Then chuſe a good meſſe of meate with pure wine, Drinke is to bée taken oft in the day, but not much at once, becauſe, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia Superabundantia putrifactionem humorum inducit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beware of all hot things in meates, as Pepper and Garlicke; for although Pepper purgeth the braine of Flegme and likewiſe the Spirituall members from viſcous and clammy humours, yee it heateth ouermuch, and Calefaction and heat cauſeth putrifaction.</p>
               <p>Bitterneſſe is more wholeſome then hot Odours or Sauours: Garlicke, although it purgeth alſo Flegme and caſteth forth euill humours, prouoketh appetite to Meate, and permitteth not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6881:15"/> any dry ayre to enter; becauſe it perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and vexeth the eyes, and heateth the head of euery one which often vſeth the ſame; therefore it cannot proue agréeable: For the Peſtilence through the vſe of hot things is oftentimes augmented and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. All kind of meates by ſo much eaſie they are of digeſtion, ſo much better they are. In the morning boyled meates are more to be commended, but in the euening roaſted. Brothes and Pulps are to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed, except they haue ſome pleaſant ſowerneſſe; for ſower meats in time of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence ſerueth to all medicines. In like manner all fruites muſt be refrained, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe of a ſower taſt, as Cheries, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granuts, or a little quantity of a Peare or Apple in place of medicine, for moſt fruits commonly induceth putrifaction. As for Spices which are commonly vſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, are Ginger, Cinamon, Cumine, Mace and Saffron, with theſe are made ſauces for the richer ſort. The poorer folkes may eate Rue, Sage, Walnuts, Parcely minced and mixed together with Vineger. Theſe doe hinder putrifaction.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, beware yée dread not Death ouermuch, but thinke well to liue: For
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6881:15"/> hée that dreads ouermuch, ſhall imagine hée féeles pricking and moouing thereof at the cleanſing places in his owne conceit, when hée féeles nothing.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſet downe ſundry meanes for preuention, It ſhall be conuenient to ſpeake of ſome ſignes and tokens, whereby a man may judge whether hée be inſected with the Peſtilence or no, and are theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, great paine and heauineſſe in the Head.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, when the body is inwardly affected with heate, and the outward parts cold and ready to ſhake, and is thirſty and dry withall.</p>
               <p>The third is, difficulty of breathing and that with paine.</p>
               <p>The fourth ſigne is, hée hath a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſléepe and can hardly refraine it, Sometime want of ſléepe and cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it.</p>
               <p>The fift is, paine and ſwelling in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, breaking forthwith ſtinking ſweats.</p>
               <p>The ſixt ſigne is, diuers and heauy lookes of the Eyes, ſéeing all things of one colour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s gréene or yellow, and the colour of the eyes are alſo changed.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6881:16"/>
               <p>The ſeauenth ſigne is, loſſe of appetite, vnſauoury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt, bitterneſſe of the mouth ſower and ſtinking.</p>
               <p>The eight is, wambling of the ſtomacke and a deſire to vomit, and ſometime vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting humours bitter and of diuers colours.</p>
               <p>The ninth is, the Pulſe beateth ſwift and déepe.</p>
               <p>The tenth ſigne is, heauineſſe and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in all the body, and ſaint, and weake limbes.</p>
               <p>The eleuenth is, the Vrine moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is troubled, thicke like beaſts wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſtinketh, but ſmell it not if you loue your health; but oftentimes the water doth not ſhew at all, eſpecially in the beginning of the Sickneſſe.</p>
               <p>The twelfth and laſt ſigne and ſureſt of all other is. There ariſeth in the necke, vnder the arme, or in the flanke a tumour or ſwelling, or in ſome other part of the body there appeareth a red, gréeniſh, or blackiſh coloured ſore: this is an apparent Signe of infection with the Peſtilence.</p>
               <p>Aſſoone as by the ſignes and tokens afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, any one perceiueth himſelfe to bée in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the venemous quality of the Peſtilence: Let him take of the foreſaid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6881:16"/> 
                  <hi>Potus Peſtilentialis Paracelſi,</hi> in quantity agréeable vnto the age of the Patient, that is to ſay; If hée be aboue Fouretéene, he may take thereof at a time, halfe an ounce or a good ſpoonefull; But if hée be of youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger yéeres, two dragmes, or more or leſſe according to the condition and reſpect of the patient, and let him bée well couered in his bed with cloathes, and ſweat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for foure or fiue houres after. Within ſixe houres after that, let him take the like doſſe and againe let him ſweat. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſixe houres are paſt, let him take the third doſſe; eſpecially, If the patient fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and perceiueth any punctions or pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings remaining: For with the third doſſe (God willing) all the venome will bée expelled and driuen forth.</p>
               <p>For thrée dayes following (the venome expulſed,) Euery morning the Patient ſhall take one doſſe of the ſayd liquor or drinke, whereby Nature may bée corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and comforted. <hi>Alexipharmacum Spagiricum</hi> will performe the ſame, of which you may giue vnto them that are aboue Fouretéene yeeres one dragme, but vnto them that are younger halfe a dragme, and that thrice in foure and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6881:17"/> twenty houres ſpace. And for thrée dayes one doſſe euery Morning, either in Wine, Roſe-vineger, or other appropriate wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>And when the Apoſtumation of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence commeth foorth, a Cataplaſme of Figges and of the fruit of Alkakengie, of each a like quantity bruiſſed together, ſhall bée applyed thereon, and it will breake it preſently; For <hi>Venenum, venonum at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wahit</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this you muſt remember, that if the Botch ariſe néere vnto the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſweate, that then you apply this defenſatiue vnto the heart vpon a fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath thinly ſpread, as broad as will couer the heart, which medicine is thus prepared.</p>
               <p>Take of good Triacle of <hi>Andromachus,</hi> halfe a dragme, of Methridate one dragme, red Sanders, of <hi>Torralemnia</hi> halfe a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Roſe-water and of Vineger, of each as much as will ſuffice to make an Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent, and let it bée applyed as aboue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
               <p>When the Apoſtume firſt appeareth, you may (if you pleaſe) take Walnuts, or Filberd nuts, Figges and Rue beaten
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6881:17"/> together, and apply it thereto.</p>
               <p>Alſo, when the ſayd Apoſtume brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and the venome penetrateth the heart, whoſe ſigne is perceiued by the liue from the Center or middeſt point of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume leading to the heart: Bruiſe then ſome of the gréene plant called Vna inuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, or Leopards haue, and apply thereto; but if it cannot bée gotten gréene but wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, then macerate it in Wine, or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, and apply it after the ſame ſort, and let it bée repeated twice or thrice ouer: For this doth extract and draw out the venome mightily, the Patient being in an agonie; and doe reuoke and call him backe as from the Graue, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth many into admiration thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6881:18"/>
               <head>Againſt the Symptomes of the Peſtilence.</head>
               <p>IN Conſtipations and Coſtiueneſſe of the belly, the patient may vſe ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue medicine; except it bée at ſuch time when the Botch or Carbuncle appeareth, any other ſores of the Peſtilence growing towards ripeneſſe: For if it bée done then, it will contrary to nature proue her intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>But the ſecond day after Sweating, If no Botch or ſore appeareth, then may hée vſe either Sena or Rhewharb, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of either. They that haue any of the Fluxes of the bowels, called <hi>Diarrhea</hi> or <hi>Diſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teria,</hi> joyned with the Peſtilence; Morning, Noone and at night, they may take halfe a ſcruple of <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> in the extract of <hi>Acorus Luteus,</hi> to the full effecting of the cure. They that are dexed with burning heates, let them dip linnen cloathes in Roſe-water vitriol, and with the juice of <hi>Semper viue,</hi> and apply to the pulfes, and when the ſame cloathes are dryed, let them bée we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againe in the ſame liquor and applyed in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6881:18"/>
               <p>And if the Patient be very dry and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, giue him of this Iulip thrée or foure ſpoonefuls at once, <hi>viz.</hi> Take of Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of the waters of Endiue, Buglaſſe, Sorrell, ſharpe Viniger, and of the juice of Lemmons of each foure Ounces, of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar one pound, boyle them a little with a gentle fire, and when it is cold, giue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to drinke thrée or foure ſpoonefuls at once. Or elſe, take of the waters of Roſes and of Buglaſſe of each thrée Ounces, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sirr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of Endine and Lemmons of each two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the Oyle of Vitriol one ſcruple, mixe them, and take them as aforeſaid. If the Patient cannot ſléepe, if after vomiting Bezoardicks, and other meanes fit to eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te groſſe humours, a man may giue the Patient <hi>Landanum Paracelſi,</hi> thrée graines thereof in <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> water, or for want thereof the Temples of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent may bée anoynted with this oyntment. Take of Vnguentum Populionis, of Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Roſarum, of Vnguentum Alaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrinum, of each half an ounce, of the oyles of Violets and of water Lillies, of eyther two dragmes, of Opium one ſcruple, or two, firſt diſſolued in Roſe-water, and then together mixed; anointing the Temples therewith,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6881:19"/> will both cauſe ſléepe, and ſtay raging. Or if you will you may vſe this.</p>
               <p>Take of the ſirrup of Violets, of the ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of of Lemmons, of the ſirrup of Popple of each one ounce, of <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> thrée dragmes, let them be mingled together, and giue therof ſometime to the patient to driu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for the foreſaid purpoſes.</p>
               <p>If through the heate of the ſtomake, the Mouth, Throate and Tongue be hot, dry and furred. Take French Barly, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folly, Violet and Strawbery leaues, of each one handfull, of Woodbind and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bind halfe an handfull, Boile all theſe in a Quart of faire water, and to the ſame Liquor ſtrained out, put thereto of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um</hi> and of <hi>Mel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſarum,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyther two ounces, of the oyle of Sulphur as much as will a little ſharpen it, and let the Patient with ſome of the ſame liquor warmed, gargarize and waſh his Mouth, Tongue and Throat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6881:19"/>
               <head>Of Fleubotomie.</head>
               <p>FLeubotomie may be vſed once in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, except age or any other cauſe prohibite it, as in women with child, or on them that are brought low by ſickneſſe, or on them that are ſubiect to any fluxe of the Belly, or on them which are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy infected with the Peſtilence, and the Botch or Sore groweth towards ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Let bloud-letting be done vpon the veine <hi>Baſilica,</hi> whether it be in the right or left arme, before he eate or drinke, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the opening of the ſame let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient bée jocund, merry and cheerefull, and to drinke good Wine or Béere, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes temperately. Neither is it lawfull nor conuenient to ſléepe the ſame day that the veine is opened, if any féeleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe infected with an Apoſtume, then let him altogether refraine ſléepe, and preuent it by walking, for in ſléepe, heate inwardly induceth the Venome vnto the Heart, and other Spirituall Members, in ſuch ſort, that ſcarce any Hearbe may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6881:20"/> reuoke the ſame venome, vnto its former ſtate, which thing happeneth not, as long as a man is in motion.</p>
               <p>But it may bée, ſome men will aske, of whom is ſléepe to be auoyded? What if hée ſhould haue a continuall ſléepe? To this I briefly anſwere, that in the time of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; if any haue an appetite to ſléepe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after he haue eaten any thing, thou ſuch deſires ought to be hindered for a ſpace, either in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Garden or Fields for one houre, &amp; then with naturall ſléep, the body may haue for one houre its naturall refection &amp; reſt. Therefore <hi>Auincen</hi> ſaith; That if a man will ſléepe, he ought to drinke a good draught before his ſléeping, becauſe in ſléepe hée at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth and draweth many humors and thoſe euill humors are repelled by the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of a good draught; But againe, if a man ſhall aske, when a man is infected how he ought to know it. To this I ſay &amp; anſwer, that a man that is infected; the ſame day he ſhall not eate much, becauſe he is repleate with euill humours, and preſently after Dinner he hath a deſire to ſléepe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth a great heat with coldneſſe, hée hath great paine in the former part of the head, but all theſe are reuoked and put away by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6881:20"/> mouing hither &amp; thither, &amp; for to walke he is not able by reaſon of ouermuch vnweldines and ſluggiſhneſſe of body, for a man infected hath alwayes a deſire to ſléepe, becauſe the venome iniernall doth perturbate and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſpirits vitall, ſo that it alwayes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to reſt, by theſe ſignes and all others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related, a man may alwayes perceiue himſelfe to bée infected. If hée will not giue credit vnto it, let him make tryall for halfe a dayes ſpace, and preſently hée ſhall féele the Apoſtume vnder his Armes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the groine, or elſe about the Eares. Therefore the chiefeſt remedie is, if a man perceiue all theſe tokens in time of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, that he ſhake off ſléepe as I haue ſaid before, for as by the reaſons before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo alledged it is manifeſt, that in ſléepe the Spirits vitall doth reſt, but the venome is ſcattered, through the membrands from one place vnto another, as I haue often obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. This being truely marked, when a man findeth himſelf infected, as ſoone as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible may be, let him let bloud in as ample manner that he almoſt ſaint thereon, for the taking of ſmall quantity of bloud ſtirreth vp the venemous quality more forcibly. If a man will not cut many veines at once,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6881:21"/> then hée ſhall ſuffer to goe ouer the ſame veyne incided as aforeſaid, euen vnto the retardation and ſtaying of the Blood.</p>
               <p>Alſo he that is let blood, whether hée be infected or not, he muſt alſo ſhunne ſléepe the whole day euen to midnight. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the ſame part of the body that the Apoſtume ſhall appeare, ſhall be made the inciſion of a veyne.</p>
               <p>As for Example.</p>
               <p>If the Apoſtume ſhall appeare vnder the right Arme, Phlebotomie ſhall bée made in the middle part of the ſame arms, from the veyne <hi>Mediana;</hi> but if vnder the left arme the apoſtume ſheweth it ſelfe, then muſt you open the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> as aforeſaid, in the ſame arme, or the <hi>Hepatien,</hi> that is to ſay; in the veyne about the middle finger. If the apoſtume be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Groyne, let a veyne be opened in the Foote, about the héele on the ſame ſide. If the apoſtume bée in the Necke, Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomize the <hi>Cephalica,</hi> about the Thumbe in the hand of the ſame ſide, or the <hi>Mediana</hi> of the ſame arme, or in the hand on the ſame ſide about the leſſer finger. If it ſhall appeare about the Eare, incide the <hi>Cephalica</hi> on the ſame ſide, or the veyne
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6881:21"/> which is betweene the fore-finger and the thumbe, leaſt many venemous vapours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the braine. Or the vayne which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the leſſe finger, or about the article, which of Phiſitians is called <hi>Baſilica.</hi> If the tumour ſhall appeare about the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der blades, heart and throat: Vſe ſcarifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations with application of Ventoſis: And firſt let blood on the <hi>Median.</hi> If the Apoſtume appeare on the backe, open the veyne called <hi>Pedia Magna.</hi> And all theſe may bée let blood, If a man haue not ſlept before the knowledge of the Apoſtumati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But if hée féele ſuch Apoſtumations after ſléeping; then bléeding ought to be made on the contrary part. As if the Apoſtume appeared in the right arme, the <hi>Baſilica</hi> or Liuer veyne; or <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diana</hi> in the leſt arme, ſhall bée ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>And if the Apoſtume ſheweth vnder the right arme, let it bée as it is ſpoken of the left arme; and ſo of other places in which the Apoſtumation appeareth. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Blood-letting is to bée vſed, let it bée alwayes done in oppoſite manner: And if hée that haue béene let blood be very weake, then may hée ſléepe after the midſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6881:22"/> of the day. And before the middeſt of the day hée ought to be in continuall motion, either riding or moderately walking.</p>
               <p>And if afterward, the Botch increaſeth feare not: For it is a token, that Nature putteth out the venemous quality, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth a man to ſoundneſſe, then may you apply ſuch remedies thereto as is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned.</p>
               <p>And if any there bée, that ſhall receiue benefit and recouery by theſe Directions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Firſt, let him thanke GOD, that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> created Medicine of the Earth to heale his people: and ſecondly, pray for mée Sinner the writer of this little Treatiſe, for to that intent I tooke the paines.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="partial_second_copy">
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6881:23"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6881:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6881:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
